דף Daf is ע Ayin 70 but we're a little behind so
we're starting on ס״ט Samekh Tet 69 at the two dots.
And yesterday I guess we had just worked through on שבת Shabbos
the issue about this arm that sticks out and that this arm
is forbidden even if it gets pulled back in and what happens
you know if that animal with that forbidden arm then gives birth
to another animal. Now we pick up on the major point of
the משנה Mishna that the שחיטה Shechita of the mother works for
the fetus and where that idea comes from. So let's take a
look. Two dots, two dots. חותך מעובר שבמעיה Chotech me-ubar she-bim-eiha about
eight lines from the bottom. מנלן, Minalan, where do you know that
the שחיטה Shechita of the mother works for the fetus? דכתיב De-chtiv
the
פסוק Pasuk says וכל בהמה מפרסת פרסה Vechol behemah mafreset parsa etc.
בבהמה אותה תאכלו ba-behemah otah tochelu amongst the animals that animal you
may eat. So the דרשה drasha is the following: בהמה בבהמה, Behemah
ba-behemah, you may eat an animal that is within the animal. Take
the word בהמה behemah at the beginning of the פסוק Pasuk and
among the animals at the end of the פסוק Pasuk and saying
that if there's an animal within another animal so if you שחט
shacht the mother then the fetus is an animal within the mother,
an animal in an animal, לרבות הולד l'rabos ha-vlad including the fetus.
הגמרא Ha-Gemara says אלא מעתה ימירו בו. Ela me'ata yamiru bo.
If you're saying that the fetus could be called a בהמה, behemah,
an actual give the name of already an animal, why cannot it
not be used in the act of תמורה? Temurah? Weren't expecting that
question. So apparently when you you know try to exchange one animal,
a קרבן Korban for another animal and you say this should be
instead of that, the תורה Torah says you're not allowed to do
that תמורה Temurah and not only are you not allowed to do
that but if you do it the second animal is the first
animal remains קדוש kadosh and the second one becomes קדוש kadosh and
it says that if you try להמיר בהמה בבהמה, lehamir behemah b'vehemah,
one בהמה behemah with another בהמה behemah and we are taking for
granted or we're going to see in a minute that if you
try to exchange an animal, a sanctified animal for a fetus in
the mother's womb it would not be effective, it would not be
a תמורה. Temurah. So now we're saying why is that if you're
willing to call the fetus a בהמה behemah then this should be
effective. אלמה תנן Almah tnan why do we teach in a משנה:
Mishna: אין ממירין לא אברים בעוברין ein memirin lo evarim b'ubarim if
I try to say the limb of this non-sanctified animal is an
exchange for this sanctified fetus if you have a fetus that had
somehow been sanctified for a קרבן Korban or the mother was sanctified
and then the fetus grew in inside the mother ולא עוברין באברים
v'lo ubarim b'evarim or the reverse the limb of a sanctified
animal of a קרבן Korban you try to exchange it for a
fetus ולא אברים ועוברין בשלמים v'lo evarim v'ubarim b'shlemim or limbs with
a full animal ולא שלמים בהם v'lo shlemim bahem or full animal
with limbs. So if you try to do any of those things
if you didn't try to do a full animal with a full
animal then it is not תמורה. Temurah. You have not done the
act of תמורה Temurah you have not transgressed and the other thing
is not sanctified. So why is that true if you are calling
an עובר ubar an actual
בהמה? behemah? אלא אמר קרא Ela amar kra so הגמרא ha-Gemara says
all right you're right forget that. We're not going to call it
a בהמה behemah we're not going to make that דרשה. drasha. Here's
how we know the fetus is permitted through the slaughtering of the
mother because the פסוק Pasuk says וכל בהמה vechol behemah any
animal אשר היא מפרסת פרסה asher hi mafreset parsa etc. אותה תאכלו
otah tochelu that you may eat. So the דרשה drasha is anything
וכל בהמה vechol behemah the דרשה drasha is like anything in an
animal, it's almost like it said וכל בבהמה. vechol b'vehemah. So we're
not calling it a בהמה בבהמה behemah ba-behemah we're not calling it
an actual
בהמה behemah as we've demonstrated but it's something in the animal. So
anything in the animal
is permitted through the slaughtering of the mother לרבות הולד. l'rabos ha-vlad.
אי הכי I hachi says הגמרא ha-Gemara if that's true now you're
going to the opposite extreme you're saying anything in the animal. So
if that's true אפילו חותך מן הטחול ומן הכליות afilu chotech min
hat-tchol u-min hak-klayot
why is it that the משנה Mishna says that if you cut
from the kidney and the spleen and you just detach it from
the animal inside the animal it's not permitted through the slaughtering of
the mother? אלמה תנן Almah tnan why do we teach in our
משנה: Mishna: חותך מן העובר שבמעיה מותר באכילה chotech min ha-ubar she-bim-eiha
mutar ba'achilah if you detach or you know dismember the fetus then
it's still in the mother's womb the שחיטה Shechita of the mother
makes it permissible. מן הטחול ומן הכליות Min hat-tchol u-min hak-klayot from
the spleen and the kidneys אסור באכילה assur ba'achilah
it's forbidden.
So according to you the דרשה drasha is anything in an animal.
So since this still remains in the animal's cavity therefore the slaughtering
of the mother should make them permissible. אמר קרא amar kra okay
so now we're going to try to get out of that. We're
not going to call this thing an animal but we're going to
try to exclude things like a spleen and a kidney. It says
אותה otah that you may eat meaning it has to be a
full thing שלמה ולא חסרה shleimah v'lo chaseirah only something that was
like an entire entity. So the fetus was a thing we're not
calling it a בהמה behemah but it was a full thing. The
spleen and the kidney were parts of something larger were parts of
the actual mother so those are not permitted when they're dismembered but
the fetus is, something that is a full thing that's in the
mother. הגמרא Ha-Gemara says okay but let's talk about other full things
that you normally would say are not permitted through the slaughtering of
the mother. אלא מעתה... Ela me'ata... אלא מעתה שוחט את הבהמה ומצא
בה דמות יונה תשתרי. Ela ma'ata, shochet et habeheimah u'matza bah dmut
yonah, tisharei. Let's say you slaughtered the animal and inside the mother
you found a fetus, but the fetus did not look like an
animal fetus. It looked like it had a bizarre shape. Now the
גמרא Gemara often when it's talking either in this case or in
נדה, Niddah, when it talks about things that are born, fetuses that
are born, that are born at an early stage, that are aborted
or whatever, it speaks about what happens if they don't, like in
the case of
נדה, Niddah, talks what if they don't look human? Do they still
create טומאת לידה tumat leidah or not? And here it says what
if it doesn't look like a בהמה, beheimah, doesn't look like a
cow, it looks like a bird. Now the question is whether the
גמרא Gemara actually assumes here that this is
something genetically different, that actually this is some non-בהמה beheimah growing inside
of a בהמה, beheimah, or maybe even if it is a בהמה,
beheimah, but if it's at a stage where it still doesn't look
like one yet, it's at this stage considered something other. So we're
not going to have to analyze that right now, but we'll accept
the fact that it says that if what you find inside looks
like a non-בהמה, beheimah, whatever they thought it actually was, but if
what's the phenotype, not the genotype, right? So if it appeared like
a non-בהמה, beheimah, it is not permitted through the slaughtering of the
mother. Only something that basically appears like a baby cow, not something
that appears like a bird. Okay, so but why is that? If
what allows it is a verse that says anything in the בהמה,
beheimah, so it wouldn't have to appear like the cow, it could
appear to be any full thing. So תשתרי, tisharei, let it be
permissible even if it looks like a bird. אלא מעתה, Ela ma'ata,
why does רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan say השוחט את הבהמה ומצא בה
דמות יונה אסור באכילה? Hashochet et habeheimah u'matza bah dmut yonah, assur
ba'achila?
If you slaughter the בהמה beheimah and you found in it something
that looked like a dove, it is forbidden because it's not an
actual cow inside of a בהמה, beheimah, so the שחיטה shechitah of
the mother does not work for it. Which you understand, right? The
שחיטה shechitah of the mother works for something that's considered to be
a natural sort of part of the mother. This is something aberrant
and it's not a natural part of the mother, so
therefore the שחיטה shechitah of the mother does not work for it.
But how can that be if your דרשה drasha is anything in
a בהמה? beheimah? So the גמרא Gemara says okay, not anything and
not just a full thing, but בעינא פרסות ליכא. beina parsot leika.
The verse again says,
it says,
well how does the פסוק pasuk begin? It says ובכל בהמה אשר
היא מפרסת פרסה ושסעת שסע שתי פרסות בבהמה אותה תאכלו. V'chol beheimah
asher hi mafreset parsah v'shosa'at shesa shtei frasot babeheimah otah tocheilu.
So it says any animal that is split-hoofed blah blah blah that
you may eat. So now the דרשה drasha is anything in an
animal, not any animal, anything in an animal, but we're still saying
the word פרסות, parsot, only something with hoofs, okay? So that's why,
it's anything that's in an animal but it's got to have hoofs.
So the גמרא Gemara says אלא מעתה, Ela ma'ata,
that's your point? קלוט במעי פרה ליסר. Kalut b'mei parah leiaser.
Let's say it don't have hoofs, let's say it only has a
hoof, right? Let's say it doesn't have split hoofs. Remember the גמרא
Gemara a few days ago spoke about what if the thing inside
of the cow actually is going to be formed with a non-split
hoof and look like a camel's hoof? Okay, so according to you,
since it doesn't have hoofs, that should be forbidden. So the גמרא
Gemara says no, הא תני דבי רבי ישמעאל כרבי שמעון בן יוחאי.
Ha tani d'vei Rabbi Yishmael k'Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai.
The תנא tanna of the דבי רבי ישמעאל, d'vei Rabbi Yishmael, which
is our ברייתא, braita, would teach like רבי שמעון בן יוחאי, Rabbi
Shimon ben Yochai, whose דרשה drasha that allows an animal, a fetus
that has only a non-split hoof within the mother, not when it's
born, when it's born the assumption according to רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
is that's forbidden, but when the fetus is a non-split hoof is
in the mother, it's permissible based on what? It also says the
word פרסה parsah בבהמה אותה תאכלו. babeheimah otah tocheilu.
So remember it says ובכל בהמה אשר היא מפרסת פרסה, v'chol beheimah
asher hi mafreset parsah, so it has the word פרסה parsah in
the singular, ושסעת שסע שתי פרסות בבהמה אותה תאכלו. v'shosa'at shesa shtei
frasot babeheimah otah tocheilu.
So it says the word פרסה parsah singular and פרסות parsot plural.
So at this stage what are we saying? Rather than saying the
famous דרשה, drasha, which we're going to try to get back to,
which is בהמה בבהמה, beheimah b'beheimah, taking the two words בהמה beheimah
so a בהמה's beheimah in a בהמה beheimah that you can eat,
but the problem with that is the גמרא Gemara says in other
places we don't call a fetus yet a בהמה beheimah by תמורה.
temurah. So therefore we're trying to say it's based on ובכל, v'chol,
but then ובכל v'chol becomes too inclusive. So it says no, it
has to be אותה, otah, it has to be a full thing,
not like a spleen or kidney. But not every full thing, it
has to look like an animal. Okay, that's because it says פרסות.
parsot. Oh, but what if it even has non-split hoofs? It says
פרסה. parsah. So now we're having any full thing that's in the
mother that has either a split hoof or an un-split hoof, so
it looks close enough to a cow, but not something that looks
like a bird, that's what can be permitted by the שחיטה shechitah
of the mother. Okay, so that's what we did to avoid having
to call it a בהמה beheimah but to get basically to where
we normally are. You had a question?
Yes, this is talking about development then.
The development, you mean when it says that it's looking like a
bird?
Or any of this because when does a
something have a non-split hoof? Yeah, so well the גמרא Gemara does
talk about the possibility of even if a cow is born with
an un-split hoof and that, you know, whether that's permissible or not,
and that's a debate of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and the opposing,
but so I don't think
in terms of development, like when does the hoof split?
Yeah, that I don't know. The גמרא Gemara is assuming the possibility,
look, it's possible. My God, we know. That human babies can be
born with a lot of
defects as it were. So the גמרא's Gemara assuming here the possibility
not just at such an early stage but it's actually something that
even were it to be born would have an unsplit hoof.
Yeah. Two questions about בהמה. behema. If I try to exchange a
בהמה behema for a קרבן korban with a fetus, you said that
I actually haven't transgressed it all even though I intended to.
Only if you tried to exchange it with a fetus, not with
a pregnant mother, but with the fetus. Right, right, yeah.
Second, you used the term בהמה, behema, does, would a,
actually forget, I just confused myself.
Okay,
so that's one answer. So we're not calling it a בהמה, behema,
we're going to get to it through the word וכל vechol and
all these other qualifiers. So רב אשימי בר אשי אמר, Rav Ashimi
bar Ashi amar, רב אשימי בר אשי Rav Ashimi bar Ashi says,
לעולם כדקאמרת מעיקרא. leolam kedekamart mei'ikara. We'll go back to the other
drasha of בהמה בבהמה, behema bebehema, a בהמה behema and a בהמה.
behema. So which is a lovely דרשה drasha and allowed us to
say it has to be a בהמה, behema, can't look like a
bird, but anything that basically is a בהמה. behema. So you had
one question, which is if you're calling it a בהמה, behema, why
does it not work for תמורה? tmura? So I'm going to have
an answer, he says. ודקא קשיא לך, udeka kashya lach, you were
bothered, אין ממירים, ein memirin,
why can you not do תמורה tmura with it if it's called
a בהמה? behema? So he says, meaning being able to do תמורה
tmura is a bad thing, because תמורה tmura you transgress and so
on. But nevertheless, why is תמורה tmura not effective? So he says,
הא מני רבי שמעון היא. ha mani Rabbi Shimon hi. This is
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon דמקיש demakish תמורה tmura למעשר. lema'aser. We know
in other places רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon compares תמורה tmura to מעשר
ma'aser because there is a פסוק, pasuk, the פסוק pasuk in general
says don't do תמורה, tmura, and when it talks about מעשר בהמה,
ma'aser behema, giving every tenth animal as a קרבן, korban, it says
again there, it repeats תמורה. tmura. It says, העשירי, ha'asiri, the tenth,
יהיה קודש לה', yiheye kodesh lashem, will be sanctified to God, לא
יחליפנו ולא ימיר אותו בטוב ברע, lo yachalifenu velo yamir oto betov
bera, don't exchange it and don't do תמורה, tmura, good for bad.
So although the תורה Torah generally says don't do תמורה, tmura, it
repeats it by מעשר. ma'aser. Why does it repeat it by מעשר?
ma'aser? שרבי שמעון sheRabbi Shimon says, well we learn some things from
it. Like for example, מעשר ma'aser is only, comes as an individual
קרבן, korban, it's not a communal, so you don't do תמורה tmura
by a communal קרבן. korban. And he has a lot of other
things he learns from the comparison to מעשר. ma'aser. So since we
normally learn things from מעשר, ma'aser, the גמרא's Gemara going to say
that's how he also knows to exclude the idea of a fetus,
because what does the תורה Torah say about מעשר? ma'aser? It says,
אשר תעבור תחת השבט, asher ta'avor tachat hashavet, that goes under the
staff, from which we learn that something has to basically walk on
its own accord under a staff, which is not a fetus. Okay,
so the גמרא's Gemara saying your big question was if you're calling
it a בהמה, behema, how come you can't do תמורה? tmura? This
is רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that learns laws of תמורה tmura from
מעשר, ma'aser, תמעט, tema'et, and learns certain, some of the laws, and
says the same way you can't do מעשר ma'aser with a fetus
because it's not walking under any staff on its own certainly, so
therefore you can't do תמורה tmura and that just solves our problem
about why even though it's called a בהמה behema you don't do
תמורה tmura with it. Yes, Bobby. Not a word? Okay fine. So
the גמרא Gemara says ודקא קשיא לך, udeka kashya lach, okay, הא
מני רבי שמעון היא דמקיש
תמורה למעשר. ha mani Rabbi Shimon hi demakish tmura lema'aser. מה מעשר
אינו נוהג באיברים ובעוברים, ma ma'aser eino noheg be'evarim uve'ubarim, the same
way מעשר ma'aser does not apply to limbs and fetuses because they
don't walk on their own accord under any staff, so אף תמורה
אינה נוהגת באיברים ובעוברים, af tmura eina noheget be'evarim uve'ubarim, the same
is true by תמורה. tmura. Okay, and that's why, so it's called
a בהמה behema yes, but nevertheless you don't do תמורה. tmura. ומנא
תימרא, umena teimra, and how can I prove to you that this
is the position of, that this ברייתא braita that said that you
don't do תמורה tmura or this משנה, mishna, excuse me, that said
you don't do תמורה tmura with fetuses is the position of רבי
שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? דתנן, detnan, because the end of the משנה mishna
says the following. We have רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi who says you
can do תמורה tmura with fetuses. He says, דתנן, detnan, the end
of the משנה mishna says, אמר רבי יוסי, amar Rabbi Yossi, רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yossi said, ולא במוקדשים, velo bemukdashim, why can you not
do תמורה tmura with fetuses? You can sanctify a limb or a
fetus, so you should be able to do תמורה tmura by a
limb or a fetus. And not only what's the story by sacrifices?
He says, אומר רגלה של זו עולה, omer raglah shel zo olah,
if you say the leg of this animal is an עולה, olah,
כולה עולה, kulah olah, once you sanctify a part of the animal
the whole thing turns into an עולה. olah. So if that can
work for an act of sanctity, so if I try to say
this עולה olah is transferred on the leg of this animal, it
should be as good as if I said it's transferred on the
whole of this animal. The same way if I sanctify the leg,
it would apply to the whole. When I try to do תמורה
tmura on the leg, and presumably the same is true if I
try to do it on the fetus. So that's why רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yossi says you can do it on, that's how, so he
disagrees. He says you can do it. At least he says on
limbs, whether he says it on fetuses or not, at least he
says it on limbs. Okay, now what does that prove to us
about the first opinion? So here's what it proves. He says, כשאומר
רגלה של זו תהא זו תחת זו, kesha'omer raglah shel zu tehei
zu tachat zu, רגלה של זו תחת זו, raglah shel zo tachat
zu, if you say
if this leg of this animal is in exchange for this קרבן,
korban, so תהא כולה תמורה תחתיה, tehei kulah tmura tachteha, the whole
animal becomes a תמורה tmura the same way yes, you can't just
limit it to a limb. But since the effect of sanctifying a
limb transfers the whole animal, so the effect of doing תמורה tmura
on a limb actually is effective and it transfers the whole animal.
Okay, so that's רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi who says you can do
תמורה tmura on a limb. From רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi we're going
to prove that the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma who says you cannot
is רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. How are we going to prove that?
Right, and again that's important. Because it's רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon who
excludes a fetus, not because it's not called a בהמה, behemah, but
because of the connection to מעשר. maaser. How are we going to
get from the fact that this dissenting opinion is רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yosi to the fact that the first opinion is רבי שמעון? Rabbi
Shimon? The following way. Says the גמרא Gemara like this. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says: למן כמהדר ליה? Leman kamahadar leh? Who is
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi talking to when he says, "Oh, won't you
admit to me that if you try to sanctify the limb, the
whole thing becomes becomes a קרבן?" korban? He says: אי לרבי מאיר
ורבי יהודה מי איתא האי סברא? Ei leRabbi Meir veRabbi Yehuda mi
eiseh hai svara? If it's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda, do they have this logic? We're going to see that
there is an exact debate about this. Forget תמורה. temurah. I take
a nice בהמה, behemah, a nice cow, and I say, "The leg
is an עולה." ola. What does it do? So רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda basically say the leg has some
sanctity of an עולה, ola, but it doesn't affect the rest of
the animal. And רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
say, "No, if I try to sanctify the leg, the whole thing
becomes it." So here's let me just tell you what the גמרא's
Gemara going to prove and then we're going to read it inside.
So it says like this: Look, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says, "No,
you can do תמורה temurah on a limb," the same way you
could sanctify a limb and it becomes the whole thing. So the
גמרא's Gemara going to say: Who's listening to that argument? Not רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה; Rabbi Yehuda; they say if you
try to sanctify a limb, it only is limited to the limb.
So the only person רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi could be talking to
is somebody who agrees with him that if you try to sanctify
a limb, the whole thing becomes transformed. Who is that? רבי שמעון.
Rabbi Shimon. We're going to see that explicitly. Ah, so now we
see that the person he's arguing with is רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon,
and now we understand why that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon does not
allow it to be with a fetus. Because רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
learns תמורה temurah from מעשר, maaser, and since מעשר maaser doesn't apply
by fetuses, תמורה temurah doesn't apply by fetuses. So this whole thing
to explain our question, how can you learn from a verse that
calls it a בהמה behemah inside the mother, then why doesn't it
do תמורה? temurah? And it says it's רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, but
it's excluded because of the comparison to מעשר. maaser. Okay, so now
let's take a look. So it can't be that רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yosi is talking to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי מאיר. Rabbi
Meir. Why is that? והתניא, Vehatanya, we taught in a ברייתא: braita:
יכול אומר רגלו של זו עולה תהא כולה עולה? Yachol omer raglo
shel zo ola tehei kulo ola? Perhaps if somebody says the leg
of this animal is an עולה, ola, maybe all of it would
become an עולה, ola, like we know that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi
is about to say. תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, the verse teaches: כל
אשר יתן ממנו להשם יהיה קודש. Kol asher yiten mimenu la-Shem yiheye
kodesh. Anything you give from it, from, you know, an animal to
God, will be holy. ממנו קודש, Mimenu kodesh, from it will be
sanctified. If you try to sanctify part of it, then part of
it is holy, from it, some piece of it, ולא כולה קודש,
Velo kulo kodesh, it doesn't all become holy just because you tried
to sanctify the leg. So the גמרא Gemara says: יכול תצא לחולין?
Yachol tetze lechulin? Maybe if it's only the leg, since it's not
the whole animal—you can't bring a leg as a קרבן—so korban maybe
you can just redeem the leg, right? You'd have a bit of
a problem because the only time you're allowed to redeem a קרבן
korban is if it has a מום. mum. This doesn't have a
מום, mum, but it can't be brought because only the leg has
the sanctity. So what are you going to do? You can't bring
it, but you can't really redeem it because it doesn't so maybe
you can just redeem it. It says: No, תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar,
the verse teaches: יהיה, yiheye, "shall be," בהוייתו תהא, behavayato tehei, it
retains its status. You can't redeem it if it doesn't have a
מום, mum, you know, but of course you can't bring it because
it's just a leg. So what do you do? הכיצד? Hakeitzad? How
do you deal with it? מוכר לצורכי עולות, Mocher letzorchei olot, so
you go ahead and you sell it to somebody who needs to
bring an עולה. ola. Charlie here needs to bring an עולה. ola.
I did this crazy thing and I sanctified the leg of my
cow for an עולה. ola. So I say, "Charlie, let's do a
deal. Buy my cow. You're going to bring it you need an
עולה ola anyway. You'll bring it as an עולה, ola, therefore the
leg will be brought as an עולה ola because it'll be part
of your עולה. ola. I'll sell I'll sell it to you. Not
only that, I'll give you a discount. You don't have to pay
for the cost of the leg." Okay, that's already sanctified, okay. חוץ
מדמי אבר שבה, Chutz midmei eiver sheba, sell it except for the
cost of that limb, and then he goes ahead and brings it
as an עולה ola and that's how we solve the problem. Okay
fine, that's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that
say that it is sanctified but only the limb you sanctified. Now
the גמרא Gemara says and then the
ברייתא braita
continues: דברי רבי מאיר ורבי יהודה, Divrei Rabbi Meir veRabbi Yehuda, that's
what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda say. רבי
יוסי ורבי שמעון אומרים, Rabbi Yosi veRabbi Shimon omrim, רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yosi and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon say: מניין לאומר רגלו של זו
עולה תהא כולה עולה? Minayin le-omer raglo shel zo ola tehei kulo
ola? How do you know it's the whole thing transformed? תלמוד לומר:
Talmud lomar: יהיה, yiheye, "shall be," which does not just mean it
keeps its status but means like it transforms the whole thing. לרבות
כולה, Lirabos kulo, all of it becomes an עולה. ola. So now
we go back. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi is saying if you try
to do תמורה temurah on a limb, it works the same way
if you sanctify a limb, the whole thing transforms. So who's he
talking to? למן? Leman? Who's listening to that argument? אי לרבי מאיר
ורבי יהודה מי איתא האי סברא? Ei leRabbi Meir veRabbi Yehuda mi
eiseh hai svara? If it's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda, they don't even they don't even agree to his assumption.
אלא לאו רבי שמעון? Ela lav Rabbi Shimon? So he's talking to
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, so what we can infer from here is
that the תנא קמא Tana Kamma who said you cannot do an
עובר uber for תמורה temurah is רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. And now
we know why. He's perhaps a בהמה בפני עצמה—an behemah biphei atzmah
עובר uber is called a בהמה—but behemah רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon won't
allow it because it is not comparable to מעשר. maaser. So the
גמרא Gemara says that's a very nice proof and it explains how
we have our דרשה בהמה בבהמה, drasha behemah be-behemah, but the גמרא
Gemara still says: לא, Lo, no, רבי יוסי טעמא דנפשיה קאמר. Rabbi
Yosi taima denafshei kamar. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi isn't talking to anybody.
He's just explaining his own reason. He says: Look, I hold you
can do תמורה temurah on a limb. Why? Because I hold you
can sanctify a limb and the whole thing transforms. So I also
hold you can do תמורה temurah on a limb. I'm not trying
to convince you. You might be רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and you don't even agree with my first assumption,
but I'm not trying to convince you. But you understand to try
to tell you my opinion. My opinion is that the same way
you can sanctify a limb, which you may or may not agree
with, you can also do תמורה tmurah on a limb and the
whole thing becomes sanctified. Okay, so we haven't really proven it whether
we have salvaged the דרשה drasha בהמה בבהמה, behema bivehema, but it
certainly is the easier דרשה drasha and that is the one that
is most frequently quoted to assume to be the basis for this.
I will say before we get onto the next משנה mishna that
if you ask why, when the משנה mishna says if you cut
the spleen and the kidney, why is it that those remain forbidden
after you שחט? shacht? So I told you earlier, and this was,
you know, רש"י Rashi said ultimately based on an earlier גמרא Gemara
and so on, actually the גמרא Gemara implied it because the גמרא
Gemara talked about it being טמא tamei and אבר מן החי. eiver
min hachai. Actually it talked about a fetus sticking out a limb.
Anyway, the one assumption is that when you cut it, it becomes
אבר מן החי, eiver min hachai, right? A fetus isn't אבר מן
החי eiver min hachai because it never was an intrinsic part of
the mother. But the spleen and the kidney are אבר מן החי
eiver min hachai and אבר מן החי eiver min hachai doesn't become
permissible just because you שחט shacht it. This discussion does not sound
like that. You notice we discussed the entire משנה, mishna, we didn't
mention the word אבר מן החי eiver min hachai once, right? And
it sounds a little bit more like that no, that you cut
them, they're not אבר מן החי eiver min hachai yet, I mean
they haven't gone—first of all, you know, they haven't left the mother,
they're still in the mother, so maybe they're not yet called אבר
מן החי. eiver min hachai. But they're not permitted through the שחיטה
shechita of the mother. They're just now pieces of meat, you know,
flopping around inside the cavity, so the שחיטה shechita of the mother
does not apply to them. The שחיטה shechita of the mother applies
to everything that's still part of the mother. It applies to the
fetus, we have a דרשה, drasha, but we don't have a דרשה
drasha to apply—we only have a דרשה drasha to apply בהמה בבהמה,
behema bivehema, not to apply to these cut-up things inside of the
cavity. The difference would be that then they would be forbidden as
what? Basically as נבילה, neveila, as meat that did not undergo שחיטה.
shechita. Right, that's what it would be as opposed to אבר מן
החי. eiver min hachai. So I just want to point out that
this גמרא Gemara never mentions the problem with אבר מן החי eiver
min hachai with the spleen and the kidney, it more suggests it's
just that the שחיטה shechita does not work for the spleen and
the kidney.
Yes. And that's important because a non-Jew could eat that.
Oh, there you go. Excellent. And it wouldn't cause טומאה. tumah. Yeah.
There you go. Okay. Now moving on to the
משנה. mishna. Okay.
Yes, Ishie has a question at this point. Sure. How do you—how
do you define אבר מן החי? eiver min hachai?
Well, that is if you cut a limb but it's—but it's, you
know, but it's exposed, meaning it's not still in the cavity. Meaning
if I cut off an arm or maybe if I stuck my
hand in and cut off a spleen or kidney but I removed
it. But it's still—not staying within the cavity, so maybe it's not
an אבר מן החי eiver min hachai yet. That's the question.
Wait, if you—if you cut it and removed
it—Yeah, if I cut an arm off, that's אבר מן
החי.
eiver
min hachai. Right. And if you cut a spleen off and I
pulled it out of the animal, that would be אבר מן החי.
eiver min hachai. What's its status when I cut it and I
leave it in the cavity of
the animal?
Oh. That's the question.
But what's the—what's the
relevance? Because—because then I'm going to שחט shacht the animal and then
I'm going to open it up and it'll still be there.
Oh, that's the question.
Right. That's the case in our משנה mishna after you שחט shacht
the animal. So our משנה mishna says no, but why not? Is
it because it's אבר מן החי eiver min hachai or is it
because no, it's a piece of meat in the cavity of the
animal that was never permitted through the שחיטה? shechita? Okay. So now
we go
on. המבכרת המקשה לילד. Hamvakeret hamaksheh liyaled. So now we are talking
about an animal that was sort of having—giving childbirth and you were
cutting it, right? It's the example of מבכרת, mivakeret, מקשה, maksheh,
difficulty in childbirth because that's why you're trying to maybe cut up
the fetus to save the mother. But now we move from—and the
question was the שחיטה shechita of the mother for the fetus. Now
we're talking about the issue about it being a firstborn. Now, actually,
the mother is not a firstborn, that doesn't matter. It's מבכרת, mivakeret,
the הפעיל, hif'il, right? It is giving birth to the firstborn. It
is the one causing the firstborn to be born. Okay, so the
child, the fetus now is a בכור bechor and the question is
the sanctity of a בכור, bechor, right? That when the fetus is
born, it becomes a בכור bechor even without sanctifying it automatically, it's
brought as a קרבן. korban. But now you have to cut it
up to save the mother. What's the status of this cut-up fetus
that otherwise would have been a בכור? bechor? So let's take a
look. המבכרת המקשה לילד, Hamvakeret hamaksheh liyaled, the animal giving birth to
a firstborn that is having difficulty in childbirth, מחתיך אבר אבר ומשליך
לכלבים. mechatich eiver eiver umashlich laklavim. You can cut it up limb
by limb—and you're not doing it to avoid the בכור bechor problem,
you're doing it because you are trying to save the
mother—but because you're cutting it up limb by limb, meaning it is—it
only becomes a בכור bechor when it's born. As each limb sticks
out, assuming it's not coming out head first, if the head first
was, it would already be a בכור, bechor, but if it's coming
not out head first, the majority has to come out for it
to be a בכור. bechor. So as each limb comes out, you
cut off each limb to save the mother and it's not yet
considered born, so it has no sanctity of a בכור. bechor. So
therefore you can throw these limbs to the dogs. יצא רובו, Yatza
rubo, once the majority comes out, then הרי זה יקבר. harei zeh
yikaver. Now it has the sanctity of a בכור. bechor. It's not
clear whether it means it's been coming out limb by limb and
now the majority of, you know, you've finally cut up enough pieces
to be the majority, or it means in a different scenario when
the majority came out at once and then you cut that off.
But anyway, once the majority... Once the majority comes out, now it's
considered a בכור bechor and it's sanctified. So even if you have
to keep on cutting, what you're cutting has sanctity of a בכור
bechor and don't throw it to the dogs, but bury it. It's
a קורבן korban that has been, you know, died, and bury it.
וניפטר מן הבכורה, unifter min habechora, but it exempts the other thing
from being, next you know, if another child comes out, you know,
next time the mother has a child, it will no longer be
a בכור bechor because once this was a birth, even though it
was a birth that came out through pieces collecting to until it
was considered a birth, but once that happens, then the mother has
given birth and therefore the next one is not a בכור. bechor.
Now right, now the גמרא Gemara does not explicit this explicitly, it
sort of implicit, תוספות Tosafot makes this explicit, points out I should
say it, right? The משנה's Mishnah a little ambiguous whether when it
says רובו rubo means at one time or through through, you know,
collecting up these little pieces became a רוב, rov, but תוספות Tosafot
proves from other cases like the גמרא Gemara is explicit, for example,
a משנה Mishnah is explicit, if a human mother is giving child
birth, and again, you know, God forbid, there's some danger to her
life and you're doing this on the fetus, that once the pieces
collect to the רוב, rov, she's considered to have be a יולדת
yoledet of giving birth and has the טומאה tumah of יולדת yoledet
and so on. So it doesn't have to be that the majority
came out at once. Even if God forbid it's coming out in
these like little piecemeal and they're being chopped off, once it's a
majority she's considered to have given birth. So here too, once it's
a majority, it has the sanctity of a בכור bechor and she
would the mother cow would no longer have a בכור bechor the
next animal that was born.
And what's the majority?
How do you measure it? That's a good question. You know, do
you go by volume? Yeah, no, the once it's the head you
don't need the majority. Once it's either the head or the majority,
you know, when it comes to טומאה tumah like for a corpse,
there's a whole question about how do you figure out the majority?
Is it
רוב מנין ובנין rov minyan uvinyan of the איברים? evarim? Like that's
the skeleton, you know, whether it's the majority of the number of
bones or the structure of the bones?
I'd have to see what the discussion is. But some way, you
know, presumably the volume majority of the entire fetus, but I'd have
to see if there's more discussion of that. But presumably it's the
volume. But no, once it's the head, then the head either the
head or the majority. So that would be a case where it's
coming out feet first, which then you explain why you're cutting it
up because coming off feet first the animal could be in danger.
Yeah.
This could be a still birth, in other words. Yeah, not in
embryonic stages where the development has to be
visible as a child or as an animal.
Right. And it could have even been a live birth until you
started cutting it up. Yeah, like a still birth,
as long as it's visible as an entity.
Right. So I mean the גמרא Gemara does say that we're not
right. And בכור, bechor, what it's important for exempting the next one
for בכור bechor is that it's not that it was viable but
just that it was considered a birth. Okay. So גמרא איתמר. Gemara
itmar. So we taught: יצא שליש ומכרו לעובד כוכבים. yatza shalish umachro
le'oved kochavim. Let's say a third of the animal came out. And
now if a non-Jew owns part of the of the firstborn, then
it's exempt from the laws of firstborn. Okay, it has to be
fully owned by a Jew. So actually one way to get out
of the laws of בכור bechor is that you sell the fetus
while it's in the mother's womb to a non-Jew. There's even ways
in which you could discussions about, you know, selling a part of
the mother, and would that also exempt the child? But anyway, here
you didn't sell it as a fetus, but as the fetus now
is sticking out its arm, you sold that arm to the non-Jew.
Okay? So יצא שליש, yatza shalish, so a third of it came
out ומכרו לעובד כוכבים, umachro le'oved kochavim, you sold it to a
non-Jew. וחזר ויצא שליש אחר, vachazar veyatza shalish acher, and then the
other third came out, or the rest of it come out, the
majority came out now. So what's the story? Does the non-Jew own
that third and you're exempt or not? So רב הונא אמר קדוש,
Rav Huna amar kadosh, that it is sanctified as a בכור, bechor,
the non-Jew did not own the third in practice. רבא אמר אינו
קדוש, Rava amar eino kadosh, no it does not get sanctity, you
sold a third to the non-Jew and it never becomes a בכור.
bechor. What's the debate? רב הונא אמר קדוש, Rav Huna amar kadosh,
it is holy, why? קסבר למפרע קדוש. kasvar lemafrei'a kadosh. Once the
majority of, remember the debate we had about ישנה לשחיטה מתחילה ועד
סוף, yeshna lishchita mitchila ve'ad sof, right? Is it considered a process
of שחיטה shechita from the very beginning or only when you finish?
So it's somewhat similar here. Once an animal, the majority of the
fetus has to come out for it to be considered born. But
once the majority comes out, do I now go back and say
that, ah, now that it's born I see that from the minute
it began coming out it was already in the process of being
born? Okay, that's the question. Or do I only say, no, it
only the process of being born and the status of being born
only begins at the majority once the majority is out? So that's
the debate. רב הונא אמר קדוש, Rav Huna amar kadosh, it is
sanctified and the selling to the non-Jew did not work, why? קסבר
למפרע קדוש, kasvar lemafrei'a kadosh, the sanctity of a בכור bechor once
the majority comes out, the sanctity then retroactively took place from the
beginning of the time it was coming out. דכיון דנפיק ליה רוביה,
dekivan denafik lei rubei, since the majority now came out, איגלאי מילתא
למפרע, iglai milta lemafrei'a, the matter is revealed retroactively, דמעיקרא הוה קדוש,
deme'ikara hava kadosh, that the sanctity began from the moment it began
coming out, ומאי דזבין לאו כלום זבין. umai dezavin lav klum zavin.
Once it was sanctified now from the moment it was coming out,
although you tried selling it, you can't sell a בכור. bechor. Once
it has sanctity of a בכור bechor you can't sell it. So
it's true sort of in historical time when you sold it it
didn't yet have sanctity. But looking now at backwards through halachic lenses
now that the majority is out we say, oh now we see
that at that time, although at the moment it wasn't sanctified, now
retroactively we're saying that it actually was sanctified and therefore the sale
was no
good. Okay. So that's what רב הונא Rav Huna said. רבא אמר
אינו קדוש, Rabba amar eino kadosh, it's not sanctified, קסבר מכאן ולהבא
קדוש, kasavar mikan u-lehaba kadosh, it is only sanctified so here moving
forward. ומה דזבין שפיר זבין, U-mah de-zavin shapir zavin, and therefore it's
only sanctified once the majority comes out. So when the third came
out, it was not yet sanctified, you could sell it. And now
that the majority came out, should it be sanctified? Well, now it's
born, but what's born is partly owned by a non-Jew. So therefore
it does not become sanctified. Is that clear? רבא Rabba says that
the sanctity takes place after the majority comes out and at that
stage part of it is already sold. רב הונא Rav Huna says
once the majority comes out, then it's sanctified retroactively from the time
it began and therefore you weren't able to sell it. Now the
same way here it leads with רב הונא Rav Huna saying it's
sanctified and רבא Rabba saying it's not, you could use their debate
and have the reverse implications in a different scenario. Let's take a
look. ואזלו לטעמייהו, Va-azlu le-tameihu, they go according to their reasoning as
expressed in a different case. What do they say? דאתמר, De-itmar, it
was
said. יצא שליש דרך דופן ושני שלישים דרך רחם, Yatza shlish derech
dofen u-shenei shlishim derech rechem, so let's say, I don't know how
this happened unless it was through cutting it up. Okay, a third
came out through Cesarean section and then the remainder two-thirds came out
vaginally, the normal way. Now you can't have it coming out whole
that way unless it means that a third came out and then
it pulled its arm back in and then you have to wonder
what status that has. But maybe a third came out and you
dismembered that third and then the rest came out the normal way.
So when it came out, what comes out through Cesarean section through
the wall of the womb is not considered having been born, right?
Born means the natural way, like from Shakespeare, right, not of a
woman born. Right. Anyway, so כיון, keivan, so therefore once two-thirds have
come out, interestingly though, although it's not considered born, we would determine
the status of the fetus once the majority is out of the
mother, whether it came out through birth or through this Cesarean unnatural
way. So a third was cut out through Cesarean, then the rest
came out vaginally, but when the second third came out, so then
the majority had come out. So now that two-thirds are out, was
it born or not born? You would say it's not born, right?
Now that a majority is out and only one third was born
and the other was not, so the majority is out but it
hasn't been born, so therefore it doesn't have sanctity. Okay. So רב
הונא אמר אינו קדוש, Rav Huna amar eino kadosh, it's not sanctified
for the reason I just described. רבא אמר קדוש, Rabba amar kadosh,
רבא Rabba says it is sanctified. What's the logic? So let's take
a look.
רב הונא אמר אינו קדוש, Rav Huna amar eino kadosh, רב הונא
לטעמיה, Rav Huna le-tameih, he goes according to his reasoning דאמר למפרע
קדוש, de-amar le-mafrei'a kadosh, that once a majority comes out, now you
retroactively say the process began from the moment it started coming out.
Well if from the moment it started coming out, that includes the
coming out
through the wall of the womb, Cesarean section, and therefore that sanctity
can't apply to that third. So therefore there's no sanctity. Okay, that's
what רב הונא Rav Huna said. ורובא קמא ליתא ברחם, U-rubba kama
leisa be-rechem, and the first half was not coming out through the
normal
way. רבא אמר, Rabba amar, רחם rechem sometimes means the womb, sometimes
it means the opening of the womb. Okay, that's why it's a
little bit confused. Meaning, coming out vaginally. So when it says ליתא
ברחם, leisa be-rechem, it doesn't mean not through the womb, actually the
first third did come out through the wall of the womb, but
it means the natural way. רבא אמר קדוש, Rabba amar kadosh, רבא
Rabba says it is. Why does that work? Let's take a look.
רבא לטעמיה דאמר מכאן ולהבא קדוש. Rabba le-tameih de-amar mikan u-lehaba kadosh.
רבא Rabba says a בכור bechor becomes sanctified
only, we don't look at the whole process. We look at what's
in front of us basically, and once the majority is out, that's
קדוש. kadosh. So he says, ah, but now that somehow is going
to mean this will be קדוש. kadosh. Why? ורובא דרך רחם נפקא.
U-rubba derech rechem nafka. Now that it all came out, a majority
did come out through the normal way and therefore it is sanctified.
Meaning what? רבא Rabba does not say I have to, I'm forced
to, go back and look at the process from the beginning. Right.
רב הונא Rav Huna says once the majority comes out, we go
back and look at the process from the beginning, we try to
label it the process of being born and the בכור, bechor, but
the key is the beginning of the process. So according to him,
when the beginning of the process was Cesarean, you're not going to
be able to call it having קדושה. kedusha. רבא Rabba does not
say we look at the beginning of the process. He says we
look at what's in front of us and if the majority is
born, then that is קדוש. kadosh. So the first third we ignore,
then two-thirds come out vaginally, that's considered to have been born. And
therefore we say that it is sanctified.
Yes. Do we—you probably answered this and I wasn't here—but do we
describe a human birth, a child of a cesarean in a different
way than you do a child
of a—there are different הלכות. halachot. First of all, a child born
through cesarean section, the ברית מילה bris milah would not override שבת
Shabbos on the eighth day, and the mother would not have טומאה
tumah of a יולדת yoledes through that. But in terms of the
status of the child, no, but in terms of to what degree
we call it כי יולד ki yivaleid that it was a natural
birth, so the פסוקים pesukim that speak about like שבת Shabbos like
ברית מילה bris milah being on the eighth day and overriding שבת
Shabbos are speak about when it use the verb יולד. yivaleid. And
the פסוקים pesukim that speak about the mother, what do you call
it, the mother being טמאה temei'ah use the verb, you know, לידה.
leidah. So we don't really call—so we don't call the act as
לידה, leidah, but it doesn't affect the status of the person or
child him or herself. Yes, Charlie.
Does the same—פדיון הבן pidyon haben still the same?
פדיון הבן, pidyon haben, yeah. Well, no, no, no, excuse me. No,
no, no. Not פטר רחם. peter rechem. Yeah, right, right, I'm sorry.
No, that's the most obvious exception. It's not פטר רחם, peter rechem,
right. It's not פטר רחם. peter rechem. פטר רחם peter rechem again,
because רחם rechem here means the normal opening of the womb, not
the wall of the womb. Right. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this. Why do they have to say it in both places?
Okay, וצריכא, utzricha, you have to tell them in both places. דאי
אשמעינן בהא, de'ee ashmueinan be'ha, had we just said in the first
case, בהא קאמר רב הונא, be'ha kama Rav Huna, that's why רב
הונא Rav Huna said his position when it's when you sold it
to the non-Jew and רב הונא Rav Huna says it's still קדוש,
kadosh, that's why he said his position, משום דלכולא. mishum de'likula. It
actually doesn't, it means the opposite of לקולא. lekula. It means because
to say otherwise would be lenient. So maybe he's just saying his
opinion that it starts at the beginning to play it safe and
to be strict. אבל בהך, avel be'hach, in this case, where we're
saying that you go from the beginning means it's not sanctified, because
it came the first third came out through the wall of the
womb, לחומרא, le'chumra, that to say that to say it the other
way would be strict, it's funny what the, it doesn't mean this
way but the other way would be strict, אימא מודה ליה לרבא,
eima modeh lei le'Rabba, maybe he'd say it the other way, maybe
he doesn't know, maybe he's just trying to play it safe either
way. So you have to tell me that he's consistent with his
opinion whether it's strict or lenient. And now the top of ע'
עמוד א'. ayin amud aleph. ואי אתמר בהא, ve'ee itmar be'ha, if
it had just said in the second case, בהא קאמר רבא, be'ha
kama Rabba, that's where רבא Rabba is going to say his opinion
that it's sanctified when it comes a third through the wall and
two-thirds natural because that's strict. אבל בהא avel be'ha in the first
case of selling to the non-Jew, maybe he would also wouldn't be
lenient, maybe he'd מודה ליה לרב הונא, modeh lei le'Rav Huna, he'd
agree to רב הונא, Rav Huna, צריכא tzricha it needs to tell
us both cases. Okay, so they're consistent, it's not about being strict
or lenient. I'm just going to stop and start again so we
have...